Finding aid to World Fairs records CA.MS.00096
Smith College Archives
World Fairs records
1893-1939
Smith College Archives
Smith College.
CA.MS.00096
0.417 linear feet (1 container)
Smith College had booths at several world fairs and expositions from the 1890s to the 1930s, giving the college unique opportunities to publicize its merits. Materials in these records include guest registers, postcards, photographs, planning memos and correspondence. This collection gives insight into how the college presented itself to the public at a relatively early stage in its life. The material also reveals some of the college's publicity strategies.
Biographical / Historical
Smith College had booths at several world fairs and expositions from the 1890s to the 1930s, giving the college unique opportunities to publicize its merits. It was one of the only women's colleges to consistently appear at world fairs. The booths highlighted Smith's history, famous figures, campus, educational opportunities, and distinguished alumnae. The four stated purposes of such displays were to 1) greet and aid alumnae who had often traveled great distances and were unfamiliar with the area; 2) attract new students; 3) "make friends" for the college; leave visitors with favorable impressions; and 4) interest potential donors. The booths were staffed by alumnae and local Smith College clubs played major roles in planning the events.
The 1893 World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago was the first time women had taken an active role in planning the fair. The Smith College booth was in the Women's Building, which brought together many booths related to women's interests and was called "one of the first major expressions of feminist consciousness" in the country.
At the 1915 Panama-Pacific Exposition in San Francisco, Smith's booth was in the Palace of Education. This time, the catchphrase was "bringing Smith to California" as the college tried to recruit West Coast students. The college took its role as the main representative of higher education for women seriously, and focused on the achievements of college educated women in the world.
The booth at the 1933 Century of Progress fair in Chicago was located at a highly visible junction in the Hall of Social Sciences. Despite early plans to have a combined Seven Sisters display, in the end Smith was the only women's college to have a booth. However, there was a lounge area for alumnae of all women's colleges elsewhere in the same building. The main attraction of the Smith booth that year was the colorful mural background painted by art professor Oliver Larkin, portraying various aspects of student life at Smith.
Scope and Contents
The World Fairs records cover the years 1893-1939. Materials included in this collection are programs, pamphlets, guest registers, postcards, photographs, planning memos, correspondence, financial reports, newspaper clippings and articles. This collection can give the researcher a good idea of the enormous effort that went into displaying a booth at a World Fair. It is also especially interesting to see how the college presented itself to the public at a relatively early stage in its life. The material reveals some of the college's publicity strategies, including what aspects of life at Smith were highlighted, and how certain questions regarding the atmosphere and lifestyle at a women's college were addressed.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The World Fair Records were donated over a period of time from a variety of sources.
Exhibitions--United States.; Trade shows--United States.; Smith College.
- World's Fair Register, 1893 (Box 182)
- World's Columbian Exposition, 1893 (Box 182, Folder 1)
- Pan Pacific Exposition, 1915 (Box 182, Folder 2)
- Century of Progress, 1933 (Box 182, Folder 3)
- Century of Progress - Finances, 1933 (Box 182, Folder 4)
- Century of Progress - News Releases, 1933 (Box 182, Folder 5)
- Century of Progress - Photographs, 1933 (Box 182, Folder 6)
- Century of Progress - Slides, 1933 (Box 182, Folder 7)
- New York World's Fair, 1939 (Box 182, Folder 8)
- Smith College Booth - A Century of Progress General Register, 1934 (Box 182)